Richard Francis Burton Papers
Richard Francis Burton Papers
1855-1891
Burton, Richard Francis, Sir, 1821-1890.
0.5 linear ft.
British explorer of India and Africa, world traveler, orientalist, author, linguist, translator of The Arabian nights. Collection includes correspondence (1855-1891); contracts with publishers; and essays by Burton. Correspondence includes letters from Lady Burton (Isabel Arundell), including some to Algernon Charles Swinburne, and letters by Burton regarding Africa and the Orient.
148879
Biographical History
Captain Sir Richard Francis Burton (1821-1890) was a 19th century British explorer, translator, Orientalist, author, linguist, poet and translator of The Arabian nights.
Born in Devon, England, Burton's early education was largely from tutors due to his family's habit of extensive and frequent travel. He went to Trinity College, Oxford in 1840; upon his expulsion in 1842 he traveled to India, where he began his lifelong study of Eastern languages, societies and customs. The following years were filled with travel and adventure, including a pilgrimage to Mecca for which Burton disguised himself as a native, an exploit which made him famous. In the 1850s he explored the interior of Somali land and made an expedition to the sources of the Nile. In 1861 he married Isabel Arundell (1831-1896) and shortly thereafter entered the British foreign service and was consul in Fernando Po, Brazil, Damascus and Trieste. In his later years Burton produced many travel books as well as translations of The Arabian Nights and an edition of the Kama Sutra in English.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Richard Francis Burton Papers are arranged in four series: correspondence, legal records, writings, and miscellany. A small portion of the papers relate to Burton's wife, Lady Isabel Burton.
Correspondence, approximately 70 items, deal with Oriental languages, translation problems, theories about Africa, mining on the Gold Coast, foreign service and the like. There are also 17 letters from Lady Isabel, three of which are to the British poet Algernon Swinburne.
Legal records consists of two agreements between publishing houses and Lady Isabel.
Writings consist of two articles and two book reviews by Burton, in both published and draft formats.
Miscellany contains a copy of a contemporary review of Burton's translation of The Lusiads and a few other items of ephemera.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically; an index to correspondents appears at the end of this inventory. Other material is arranged alphabetically by type or title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- British; Burton family.; Burton, Isabel, Lady, 1831-1896.; Burton, Richard Francis, Sir, 1821-1890.; Swinburne, Algernon Charles, 1837-1909.; Authors and publishers -- Contracts and specifications.; Explorers.; Translators.; Africa -- Discovery and exploration.; Clippings (information artifacts); Contracts.; Correspondence.; Essays.; Manuscripts for publication.; Authors.; Explorers.; Translators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Frederick P. Hier, 1955.
Purchase, 1955-1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1855, 1865, 1868-1891, undated, 21 folders (Box 1)
  - Baddeley, St. Clair, 1883-1889; album of letters from Burton (Box 1)
- Legal records
  - Agreement, I. Burton with H. King & Co., 1875 (Box 1)
  - Agreement, I. Burton with W. Tinsley, 1868 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia - Scrapbooks
  - "Agents", 1870-1888; primarily accounting documents in scrapbook form, with some legal material (Oversize 2)
    See also Commissions, below, for items which were laid in and have been foldered separately for preservation purposes.
  - "Arabian Nights", 1885-1886; clippings of reviews of the 1885 book 'Arabian Nights', including correspondence (Oversize 1)
  - "Burton's Lusiads", 1876-1889; clippings and reviews of the 1880 book of Burton's, including correspondence (Box 1)
  - [Clippings], 1875; 1886-1887,; undated (Oversize 2)
  - Commissions [from the 'Agents' scrapbook], 1843; 1846,; 1872,; 1883 (Oversize 2)
    These items were originally laid in the "Agent" scrapbook above, but have been foldered separately for protections. Items include letters from the Governor Council in Bombay for Burton's Indian Army service, a letter of appointment as Consul to Austria in Trieste, and an appointment letter as Knight Commander in the Order of Saint Michael and Saint George from Queen Victoria.
  - "Durrants and other press clippings 1893, chiefly on 'Life' ", 1885-1896 (Oversize 2)
  - "The Inner Life of Syria, Palestine, and the Holy Land", 1975-1876; clippings and reviews of the 1875 book by Lady Isabel Burton (Mrs. Richard Burton) along with correspondence (Box 1)
  - "Isabel Burton Scraps also Sir Richard's from June'88 to February '89", 1880-1881; 1888-1889 (Box 2)
  - [Lady Burton] Scrapbook, 1886-1888; clippings mainly about Isabel Burton's translations of her husband's works (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Jose Basilio de Gama, the Man and the Poet, circa 1878 (Box 2)
    - This is How the War Began, 1882 (Box 2)
  - Book reviews
    - The Life of Stratford Canning by S, Lane-Poole, 1888; reproduction from The Academy; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Travels in Tunisia by A. Graham and H. S. Ashbee, 1888; drafts and reproduction; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Review of The Lusiads, other items, 1861-1881 (Box 2)
Index to correspondence
Isabel Burton Dec 1881 12 Jan [no year] to Edwin de Leon, 14 Sep 1890, Trieste to I. A. S., Dec [no year] to Miss Smith, 27 Aug 1875 to Euphemia Mackay Smith, 27 Nov [no year], London to Euphemia Mackay Smith, 28 Sep 1884, Trieste to Mrs. Suverkopf, 9 Mar 1885, Trieste to Mrs. Suverkopf, 20 Apr 1885, Trieste to Mrs. Suverkopf, 2 Jun 1890, London to Mrs. Suverkopf, 7 Apr 1891, London to Algernon Swinburne, 3 Aug [no year], London? to Algernon Swinburne, 7 Jul 1874, Trieste to Algernon Swinburne, 3 Dec 1879 to Mr. Tinsley, 1869 to Mr. Watts, circa 1875 to Mr. Watts, 24 Sep 1875, Trieste
Richard Burton [no date], 3 items 24 Mar [no year], Trieste 30 Jun [no year], Trieste 23 Nov [no year], at sea 13 Dec [no year], Lisbon 25 May 1877, Trieste 3 Jun 1877, Trieste 5 Dec 1884, Trieste to E. Allen, 29 Sep 1865, London to E. Allen, 26 Mar 1886, Trieste to J. B. Andrew, 18 Jan 1884, Trieste to St Clair Baddeley, 26 Jun 1883, Trieste to St Clair Baddeley, 25 Jul 1883, Trieste to St Clair Baddeley, 23 Dec 1883, Trieste to St Clair Baddeley, 1 Apr 1884, Trieste to St Clair Baddeley, 30 Apr 1884, Trieste to St Clair Baddeley, 18 Sep 1884, Trieste to St Clair Baddeley, 3 Dec 1884, Trieste to St Clair Baddeley, 4 Mar 1884, Trieste to St Clair Baddeley, 15 Oct 1887 [?], Trieste to St Clair Baddeley, 11 Apr 1889, Trieste to St Clair Baddeley, 18 Sep 1889, Trieste to William Beke, Athenaeum Club London, 27 May 1875 to Lord Broughton, London to Andrew Chatto, 5 Jun 1882, London to Cotton, 7 Nov [no year], Geneva to Cotton, 12 Dec 1885, Tangier to James S. Cotton, 12 Aug 1865, London to James S. Cotton, 24 Oct 1869, Trieste to James S. Cotton, 11 Sep 1885, London to James S. Cotton, 30 Jan 1886, London to James S. Cotton, 13 Jul 1886, London to James S. Cotton, 22 Sep 1886, London to James S. Cotton, 20 Nov 1888, Geneva to James S. Cotton, 10 Jan 1889, Territet, Switzerland to James S. Cotton, 23 Jun 1889, London to the editor of The Academy, 18 Jun 1888, Switzerland to W. F. Kirby, 16 Aug 1888 to Mr. Irvine, 27 Sep, [no year], Pall Mall to Mr. Mon [?], 22 Mar 1870 to Mr. Monson, 27 Apr 1873, Trieste to Mr. Ravenstein [?], [no date] to Stratford Redcliff, 22 Jul 1855 to Mr. Saunders, 2 Mar 1874, Trieste to Mr. Saunders, 19 Mar 1874, Trieste to Smith, Elder & Co., 28 Oct 1875 [?] to Lady Stangford [?], 30 Sep [no year] to Mr. Suerth [?], 17 May 1877, Trieste to Reginald Talbot, Athenaeum Club London, 1878 [?] to Mr. Trikley, 1 Jun [no year], Trieste to Wilson, 21 Mar 1865